<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before His Excellency, the Ld. Lieutenant and the two Houses of Parliament in Christ's-Church, Dublin when they first met there together on Sunday, October 16, 1692 / by John, Lord Archbishop of Tuam.</title>
            <author>Vesey, John, 1636-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07840643</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07840643</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1217:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before His Excellency, the Ld. Lieutenant and the two Houses of Parliament in Christ's-Church, Dublin when they first met there together on Sunday, October 16, 1692 / by John, Lord Archbishop of Tuam.</title>
                  <author>Vesey, John, 1636-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Clavel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Publish'd by His Excellency's special command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges XVII, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40137:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40137:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Before His <hi>EXCELLENCY</hi> THE L<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> Lieutenant AND THE Two HOUSES of PARLIAMENT, IN <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s-<hi>Church, DUBLIN;</hi> When They Firſt Met there together: On <hi>Sunday, October</hi> 16. 1692.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By JOHN Lord Archbiſhop of T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd by His Excellency</hi>'s <hi>Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church Yard,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:40137:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40137:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JUDG. XVII. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In thoſe days, there was no King in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but every Man did that which was Right in his own Eyes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Book of <hi>Judges</hi> contains Memorials of the State and People of the Jews, from the Death of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the Time that <hi>Eli</hi> Judged <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> with whoſe Government the firſt Book of <hi>Samuel</hi> begins, and carries on their Hiſtory. We have here an Account of many Viciſſitudes of their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and of many very Remarkable Paſſages con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Manners and Behaviour, the Sufferings and Deliverances of that Stubborn and Apoſtatizing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: From the day that they left <hi>Egypt,</hi> they were on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Turn, murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> their Deliverer; all their Grievances are put to his Account: If they at any time want Fleſh, or Bread, or Water, they immediately charge him with miſ-management, &amp; wiſh they had ſtill continu'd Slaves, ſo they might have eaten Onions, and Garlick, and Fleſh in <hi>Egypt:</hi> So that God was forc'd often to ſtop their Mouths by Miracles, and ſometimes to vindicate the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of his <hi>Servant,</hi> by extraordinary Judgments on thoſe that <hi>Rebell'd</hi> againſt it: So difficult a thing it was, to keep them to their Duty, even when <hi>Moſes</hi> was King in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurun,</hi> and was Conducting them from Bondage into Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40137:3"/> But they had not long paſt over <hi>Jordan,</hi> and Enjoy'd Reſt from their Enemies, before they fell to their old Trade. They ſerv'd the Lord all the days of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that out-lived him; but theſe were ſcarce Cold in their Graves, and but juſt gather'd to their Fathers, when there aroſe another Generation, which knew not the <hi>Lord,</hi> but did evil in his ſight, and follow'd other <hi>Gods;</hi> inſomuch, that his anger often waxed hot, that they could not ſtand againſt their Enemies. Nevertheleſs, upon their Repentance, God ſtill rais'd them up <hi>Judges,</hi> and delivered them all the days of the <hi>Judge:</hi> But as ſoon as he died, they again corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves, more than their Fathers, and ceaſed not from their own doings, nor from their ſtubborn way.</p>
            <p>This is the Account we have of them, in the Second Chapter, which deſcribes the Heads and Contents of the Book following; which is fill'd with little elſe but ſuch like various Turns of their Affairs, of their Sins and their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and of their Repentance and Deliverance.</p>
            <p>The Text is an Hiſtorical Remark, which the Collector of theſe Paſſages makes, of a certain <hi>Inter-Regnum,</hi> or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terciſion in their Civil Government, and of the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that Naturally and Uſually attend ſuch a State and Frame of Things. And accordingly, I ſhall take an Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to offer to your Conſideration the great miſery of a People, when they are without reſtraint from civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Which I ſhall with all plainneſs endeavour to lay before you, from two Heads of Diſcourſe, which are obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Here is a Vacancy in the Throne; <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. A General Debauchery, or Univerſal Depravation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40137:3"/> of Manners; <hi>Every Man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When we have viewed and conſidered theſe Particulars, I ſhall in a few Practical Inferences bring them home to our own Doors, and there leave their Application.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Here is a Vacancy in the Throne: <hi>There was in thoſe Days no King in</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>By the word <hi>King</hi> in this Text, we are not, I conceive, to underſtand that Form of Government only which we call a Monarchy, but Civil Government in general; if the Text did intend that Form preciſely and excluſively of all others, it would, I confeſs, be the ſtrongeſt Argument of the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Uſefulneſs thereof, and a reflection upon all other Models, as being leſs ſufficient for their ends. We might from ſuch an Expoſition infer, That the <hi>Monarchical</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is the moſt Powerful and Effectual Reſtraint to the Paſſions and Vices of Men. As if we ſhou'd ſay, There were other Governours, the ſtanding Council of the Great <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> and other Inferiour <hi>Judicatories;</hi> but theſe could not check the inſolencies of Men, nor ſtop the courſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety or violence; theſe could not hinder, or durſt not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Riots and Unlawful Aſſemblies of the Wicked and Unruly Sons of <hi>Belial.</hi> There was no <hi>King,</hi> and therefore every Man did as he pleas'd, as if no Lord were over them.</p>
            <p>But I conceive ſuch an Expoſition is too narrow, and not altogether true: For, as <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>Prov.</hi> XXX. 27. <hi>The Locusts who have no King, yet go forth all of them by Bands.</hi> So, other Conſtitutions of Government may have Unity, and order and ſtrength, to enforce their reſpective Laws; and the Finger of their <hi>Diſcipline</hi> is found ſometimes to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40137:4"/> heavier than the Loins of <hi>Monarchy;</hi> the Generoſity and Clemency of Kings (at leaſt of ſome Kings) Diſpenſing in ſome matters with a rigid conformity to their Laws; while others who affect a ſhew of more liberty, prove generally more ſevere Exactors of obedience. And therefore, by <hi>No King in Iſrael,</hi> I am content you may underſtand a Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Civil Authority in general, and not of any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Form of its Adminiſtration. So that, <hi>No King,</hi> ſhall ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie no Government in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But then, this kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being here put to ſignifie any other, we may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably conclude, Either</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this, <hi>viz.</hi> A <hi>Monarchy,</hi> is the beſt of all the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral kinds, the moſt apt and ſufficient for its ends, <hi>Parcere Subjectis, &amp; Debellare Superbos,</hi> for <hi>the Terror of Evil Doers, and the Praiſe of them that do Well.</hi> Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That, that Government by which God preſided over the Jews, in the times of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and the <hi>Judges,</hi> did more reſemble that of a King, than any other ſort of adminiſtration, whether of Ariſtocracy or Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And therefore we may have leave to think, that ſuch a Paternal Government in a Gentle &amp; well-temper'd <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> is moſt like the divine <hi>Theocracy</hi> over that Nation, and conſequently, where ever it obtains, in any other, is moſt Acceptable and Pleaſing unto God, as the neareſt Approach to the <hi>Pattern in the Mount,</hi> the primitive model &amp; Scheme which he contriv'd for his own People: And therefore if any Form of Government be of Divine Right, more than another, ſuch a kind of Monarchy bids faireſt for the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, as being a Copy from the Divine Original. The rays of Soveraignty did not indeed dazle the eyes here, ſo much as in the Tyrannies of the Nations, but they were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40137:4"/> more Benign, and better ſuited to the Nature and Genius of a <hi>free</hi> People: The circumſtances of Majeſty were not ſo glittering and gaudy, nor the power ſo Abſolute and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotical; but was ſufficiently qualified to anſwer all the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities both of Prince and People. Power is a wild and often a Deſtructive thing, if it be not fix'd by Law, and ſweeten'd by ſome Allay; and it becomes not only more uſeful and Beneficial, by being ſomewhat Limited and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcrib'd, but alſo more durable and ſtrong, by the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs of the People to live under it, where it is their Intereſt to ſupport and Maintain it, as well as Duty to obey it.</p>
            <p>But in this Government of the Jews, there could be no defect; every want was ſupply'd by the ſpecial <hi>Providence</hi> of the All-Wiſe and Almighty <hi>Monarch:</hi> For <hi>when the Lord rais'd them up Judges, the Lord was with the Judge, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd them out of the Hands of their Enemies all the days of the Judge,</hi> Chap. II. 18. All the defect was in the Froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the people, when they would not <hi>hearken to their Judges,</hi> Verſ. 17. but went a Whoring after other Gods; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inventing new Gods, or new-ways of worſhip, after the faſhion of their neighbours, &amp; at laſt throwing off, with their Religion, even their form of civil Polity, both which God had inſtituted for them. Thus at one time, as ſoon as <hi>Moſes</hi> turn'd his back, they cry out to <hi>Aaron, Make us Gods to go before us;</hi> and of their Idols ſo made, <hi>Theſe be thy Gods, O Iſrael;</hi> and at another time to <hi>Samuel,</hi> for <hi>a King to Rule them, after the manner of the Nations.</hi> And theſe things became matter of Gods high and juſt Diſpleaſure againſt them; not that ſuch a form was ſimply, and in it ſelf, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, but becauſe they <hi>were given to Change,</hi> and grew weary both of the worſhip which he had preſcribed for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40137:5"/> them, and the Government by which he had deliver'd them at firſt out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and carried them into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and there frequently reſcu'd them from ſuch as oppreſſed and held them in Subjection. The provocation had been equal, to have deſir'd a Parliament, or any other Regimen, than that which God himſelf had choſen for them; and this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the reaſon he gives of his diſpleaſure, to <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> VIII. 7. <hi>For in ſo doing they have not rejected thee but me, that I ſhould not Reign over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſaid thus much of the firſt thing in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> the diſſolution of the civil Government among the Jews, or the Vacancy of the Throne; I need not trouble you with the enquiry about the period of time to which this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation refers; about which, I cannot find that Agreement on which one may build any certainty: But certain it is, it could not be after the times of <hi>Eli</hi> and of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> though it is ſo placed in the Hiſtory, becauſe we find <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> the Son of <hi>Eleazer</hi> was alive, and attended the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, even after this, <hi>Chap.</hi> XX. 28. The things therefore here Recorded, and in the following Chapters of this Book, are moſt probably conceiv'd to happen ſoon after the death of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and the Elders that were Contemporary with him; when, as you already heard, they forſook the Lord, and God forſook them; and leaving them without Rule and Government to <hi>do what was right in their own Eyes,</hi> they became an eaſie Prey to every Tyrant.</p>
            <p>But it does not much concern us to know when thoſe days were, if there were at any time ſuch days, in which there was <hi>No King in Iſrael:</hi> And that there were ſuch, appears by the frequent mention of this Phraſe, in ſeveral parts of this Book; the Writer whereof ſeems not ſo Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical about the Chronology, as the matters he relates; as not confining himſelf ſo much to the Laws of Method, as the ſimplicity of Truth.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40137:5"/>
            <p>And ſo I come, from conſidering the Vacancy in their Government, to view the Conſequence of ſuch a State.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In the Second Point in the Text, which is this, An univerſal Debauchery and Depravation of manners; and who indeed could expect other? Who, that conſiders how difficult it is, even with Bit and Bridle, to reſtrain the hard mouth of the multitude? It will try the Patience, the Wiſdom, the Courage of the moſt able and experienc'd Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, even in the beſt Governments, when they are Arm'd with Power, and bear not the Sword in vain, to quench the Fire of Ambition, and keep down the Paſſions of Men from boyling over into Luſt, and Rage, and Revenge: But when there is none to guide the Chariot, to Addreſs the Motion, to check and arreſt the <hi>Furies</hi> that draw it, into what precipices will they not run? God help thoſe that ſit in the One, or ſtand in the way of the Other. This State of things is Deplorable, but 'tis unavoidable from the Other; every Man will then do what is right in his own Eyes. Whether this Expreſſion does more fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Sinful or the Miſerable eſtate of a People, is a queſtion; but that it does both; I think is none.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It does import the Sinfulneſs and Wickedneſs of a People walking by this Rule: For to do what is right in our own Eyes, is what we daily confeſs to be our Sin, in <hi>following too much the Devices and Deſires of our own Hearts.</hi> It is an Expreſſion that is beſt meaſur'd by it's contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> To do what is <hi>right in the ſight of God:</hi> And therefore we are Commanded, <hi>Numb.</hi> XV. 39. to ſeek his <hi>Statutes,</hi> and not to go after our own <hi>Hearts,</hi> and our own <hi>Eyes;</hi> and throughout this Book, theſe Phraſes are ſet in Oppoſition to each other. The Phraſe indeed, conſider'd abſtractively, is capable of a better ſence, to follow the Conduct of Right
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40137:6"/> Reaſon; but it is plain, that cannot be the Conſtruction here, but the contrary: And I think there is no Expreſſion that gives us a more full and compleat Character of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or a People wholly abandoned to a Vicious, Profligate and Senſual Life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It does as neceſſarily imply the Miſerable Eſtate of any People: For no Man is ſecure of any thing, though never ſo dear or valuable. The World is too narrow for the Ambition and Avarice of Men: They will not gaze, like other Beaſts, in common; but every man would have a property in all: So that every man muſt be perpetually on his guard againſt his Neighbour; and none can taſte or enjoy his property, for fear of looſing it. Every Man then, will be a <hi>Cain</hi> in his Family, an <hi>Abſolon</hi> in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and an <hi>Iſhmael</hi> in the World: <hi>His Hand againſt every Man, and every Mans hand againſt him.</hi> There needs not many words in a matter whereof all Men are convinc'd: For if every Man do what he thinks right, as he pleaſes, and as he is able, no man can be long pleaſed, or ſecure, of his Property, his Liberty, or his Life: Men will grow, without Religion and Law, more deſtructive than Beaſts without reaſon; and neither of theſe are ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this Caſe, to have any part: Grace here is turn'd into Wantonneſs, and Religion is uſed only as a Vizard to deceive; Reaſon is turn'd into Craft, and Power abus'd to Oppreſſion; the Weak become the prey of the Strong, and the Simple of the Subtile; Strength is the only Law of Juſtice; and he that Suffers, is always in the Wrong: And ſurely there is not a more miſerable Condition in the World, than to live in ſuch a State of <hi>Anarchy.</hi> The moſt cruel Tyranny is more Tolerable, by how much it is better to be a Slave to one, than every Man. Men would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40137:6"/> rather chooſe to open a Paſſage and let out their Lives, than to be in ſuch continual Torment about them: They would rather ſtrip themſelves of all Being, if they could, or venture their condition in another World, than live in this upon ſuch Terms. And yet, with how Pleaſing a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation does this Common wealth of <hi>Libertiniſm</hi> entertain many Imaginations? They have nothing but Golden Dreams, they already wallow in Wealth, they ſwim in Pleaſure, and are Maſters of all they can deſire: But alas! They conſider not that others have the ſame fancies and appetites; and while every man graſps at all, none can hold any thing faſt.</p>
            <p>And that none may think I have repreſented things in falſe colours, let us put our Eye to the Perſpective, and look upon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by the light of this Text, and we ſhall behold them all <hi>Chaos,</hi> deformity, and confuſion, both in their Religious and Civil Affairs.</p>
            <p>In the Story here before us, we find <hi>Micah</hi> and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buſie and zealous about their Graven and Molten Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, their Houſe of Gods, and their Ephod and Tera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim, making his Son a Prieſt, who was not of the Tribe of <hi>Levi.</hi> For the <hi>Congregation is holy,</hi> ſaid <hi>Korah,</hi> and every man has the Spirit. In the Verſe after the Text, we find a <hi>Levite</hi> Inveigl'd, to give the more Credit and Countenance to the Idolatry. Tempted by neceſſity, as may be conceiv'd by the Salary this Chaplain was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with, <hi>viz.</hi> Ten Shekels of Silver <hi>per Annum,</hi> a Suit of Cloaths and his Dyet. So that he, that was but a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the Prieſt in the Divine Appointment, is Conſecrated a Prieſt, by <hi>Micha</hi>'s order; and by the ſame Rule, the Prieſt may become a Biſhop. And as <hi>Micha</hi> here, ſo we find a great part of a Tribe Seduced into the ſame Sin, <hi>Chap.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40137:7"/> XVIII. 19. Thus the Divine Inſtitution will be deſpis'd, and all Order inverted in Religion, if every man may do what is right in his own Eyes. Every Man will take Honour to himſelf, without being call'd as <hi>Aaron,</hi> will affect the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, as well as <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> or <hi>Aerius,</hi> will be an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or a Prophet, have a Pſalm or a Hymn, a Way and Mode of Worſhip by himſelf; and the unity of Religion ſhall be divided and multiply'd not according to the Number of our Cities or Families, but of Perſons. Every man will Cry <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Eſteem it a fine thing to be Celebrated for an Author and a Setter forth of new and ſtrange Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and applaud themſelves for their own happy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, whereof there are no Footſtepts in any of the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions or Dotages of the Ancients. There is not more Pride, in being firſt in a Faſhion, than being ſingular in an opinion. Such is the carnality of ſome minds, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more delightful to them, than, as the Scripture Phraſes it, to <hi>Run a Whoring after their own Inventions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor were the <hi>Jews</hi> more unhappily led by this Liberty into Apoſtacy from their Religion, than into the vileſt and moſt ſhameful Immoralities; of which the lewdneſs of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> in all its Circumſtances and Conſequences, is an Inſtance, without a Parallel. And the ſame Reaſon is aſſign'd in the concluſion of the Hiſtory, as ſure there was <hi>no King, but every man did that which was right in his own Eyes. Judg.</hi> XXI. 25.</p>
            <p>But the evil does not reſt here, for their Idolatries and Wickedneſs is puniſht, with Civil Wars among themſelves, and Invaſion from abroad. The Luſt of the <hi>Benjamites,</hi> kindled the Rage of the other Tribes into ſuch a Flame, as almoſt conſum'd a Tribe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Nor was their Miſeries only from a Civil War, but from Foreign Enemies: While
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40137:7"/> they forſook God, who was their Strength, and every one diſpleas'd him, by doing what was pleaſing to himſelf, their <hi>divided houſe could not ſtand,</hi> but lay open to the Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of every powerful Prince, who thought fit to advance the <hi>Glory of his Arms,</hi> in their Conqueſt and Deſtruction. And thus they became a Prey to <hi>Chuſhan</hi> the <hi>Meſopotamion</hi> and <hi>Eglon</hi> the <hi>Moabite,</hi> and to the many other Lords, who in their turns rul'd over them, almoſt to the ruine of their Nation. Had not God ſent them frequently Signal and unhop'd for deliverances.</p>
            <p>Having entertain'd your patience on the two particulars, I propos'd to diſcourſe of: Give me leave to make a few Inferences from what has been ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">I. And Firſt, this ſhews an abſolute neceſſity of Civil Power, and a due Execution of Penal Laws, for the well Governing of any People. Since theſe only can ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly curb and reſtrain this Maxim of the Libertine, which if purſu'd, muſt neceſſarily deſtroy all our moſt Important Intereſts of Religion, of Liberty and Property. And all theſe are neceſſary. As good no King, as no Law; no Law, as no Execution.</p>
            <p>In the Caſe before us, we find the want of <hi>Civil</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to be the Reaſon of all the Sins and Miſeries of the Jewiſh Nation. They had the beſt Religion, then, in the World, and the beſt Laws for their uſe. And <hi>Phinehas</hi> the High-Prieſt ſtood before the Altar, <hi>Chap.</hi> XX. 28. in thoſe days when there was no King.</p>
            <p>But though he was a man famous for his Zeal, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> for his Faith, for it was <hi>Imputed to him for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> and we cannot imagine he was idle in that high Employment; yet neither his Courage nor his Piety could ſtem the Torrent of Vice and of Idolatry, by the <hi>Power purely Spiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40137:8"/>
            <p>Where Men have Faith to believe Eternal Rewards and Puniſhments, the Weapons of the Religious Warfare are indeed mighty, and of great Efficacy to the pulling down of ſtrong holds. But even our Saviour could do no mighty Works in ſome Places, becauſe of Mens unbelief; nor can the Eccleſiaſtical Conjurers work Miracles of Reformation on all men, for the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>But all Men have Senſe, though <hi>all men have not Faith;</hi> and the Athieſts fears Death, that does not fear God; and looks on that as a real Evil, though he thinks Hell Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments but a painted Fire. The Cure therefore of theſe Evils, of Idolatry, of Atheiſm, Lewdneſs, and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; which, we are told in <hi>Job,</hi> are <hi>Iniquities to be puniſh'd by the Judge;</hi> is not to be expected from the Spiritual Sword, unleſs the <hi>Secular Arm</hi> aſſiſt it, by delivering them over to Temporal Puniſhments, as God did to Satan, in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Diſcipline, <hi>that they may learn not to blaſpheme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Miſchief of this principle, of doing every one what is right in his own Eyes, ſhews the unreaſonableneſs of thoſe that contend for an Indefinite Liberty, either in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious or Civil Matters under a Stated and Well-ſettl'd Government; for it is the firſt end of Law and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bound and limit ſuch a Liberty. And if Men will not be confin'd by the Socity in which they live, they Cancel the Obligations to which they are ſuppos'd to have conſented, by entering into it; and ſo endeavour to Sap and Undermine the Foundation on which it ſtands; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently expoſe themſelves and others to the ſame Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies and Inſecurities they were in, when there was no Government. It is therefore the Intereſt of Government, and of thoſe that are Protected by it, joyntly to oppoſe ſuch a Principle as will deſtroy both. And when a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40137:8"/> is ſo Supine and Careleſs as to ſuffer Men to ſpeak, Write, or Act, as they liſt, it is neither true to it ſelf, nor juſt to thoſe that depend upon it; but ſeems to Conſpire with the Enemy to its own Deſtruction: For as, when there was <hi>No King in Iſrael,</hi> every Man did what was <hi>right in his own Eyes;</hi> it is as viſible if every man be allowed to do ſo, there cannot long be <hi>a King in Iſrael.</hi> Men do not put out their Eyes, when they enter into Society; but they muſt not walk afterward ſo much by the <hi>Light within,</hi> in things Lawful, as by the light of <hi>Authority,</hi> in things that are to be done; and the Light of <hi>Faith</hi> in the Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Scriptures, in things that are to be believ'd. And as wiſe Governments will not abridge the liberties of Men, which they have by the Charter of <hi>Nature,</hi> or of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which they enjoy, by that of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what is neceſſary for the Peace or Good Order of the Community; ſo neither ſhould men be clamorous for being circumſcrib'd in ſome few things in their own Nature per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly indifferent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the want of Civil Government be ſo great an Evil, Then it is both the Duty and Intereſt of any People, who are fallen into ſuch a Circumſtance, immediately to apply the proper Remedy, by filling the Vacant Throne by a free Election, where they have Power ſo to do; or Peaceable Submiſſion to thoſe, who have a Right without it. And the Publick neceſſity of affairs, the <hi>Salus Eccleſiae &amp; Salus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi> does both Require and Juſtifie their doing ſo, as well for Gods Honour, as their Countrey's ſafety.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If the want of Civil Government be an occaſion of ſo much wickedneſs &amp; miſchief, what great reaſon have theſe Nations to bleſs Almighty God, for the Reſtraint he put upon the hearts and hands of Men, when theſe Kingdoms were left in ſuch a State? Though in ſome Places the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proceeded to ſome Exceſs, yet how little miſchief was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40137:9"/> done, in compariſon of what all reaſonably fear'd would have come to paſs? When the People were left without Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and an Army was disbanded, but not diſarm'd, it could be nothing leſs than the incontroulable Dominion which God has over the hearts of men, that Reſtrain'd their Spirits, and chain'd up their deſires, from the utmoſt Violence, even from ſheathing our Swords in one anothers Bowels. But on the contrary, the men whoſe hands were mighty, found nothing; while the Multitude, apt enough at other times to run to do evil, now generally <hi>ſtand ſtill to ſee the Salvation of God;</hi> and God choſe (not in the Wind, and in the Fire, but) in a ſoft ſtill Voice to ſpeak Peace to his People.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When there was no King in <hi>England,</hi> but the People were left as Sheep without a Shepherd; and thoſe in <hi>Ireland</hi> were expos'd to the Fury of their implacable and invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Enemies; when the Ship was left to run a Drift among Rocks and Sands, without a <hi>Pilot,</hi> What reaſon have we all to rejoyce, and to praiſe God, who has committed us to the Care of ſuch a <hi>Shepherd,</hi> who has put the Helm into ſuch a hand, as hath hitherto ſo ſteer'd the good Ship be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all difficulties, that we may comfortably hope he will at length carry her into a ſafe Harbour?</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, and bleſſed be the Name of Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, this Days Aſſembly opens to us a fair proſpect of our being upon the Borders of Better Times than we have yet ſeen. We are not, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Text, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King, nor without a Prieſt, nor without God in the World,</hi> as ſome, in ſo charging us, have lyed unto God. God has reſtor'd our Religion and our Monarchy, our Laws and our Law-makers; <hi>our Judges, as at the Firſt; and our Counſellors, as in the beginning.</hi> I hope we ſhall not be like them, in the other Part, by doing every one, <hi>That which is right in our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40137:9"/> own Eyes;</hi> ſeeking our ſelves, our pleaſures, and our gains from our Quarters, our private Intereſts either of parties, or perſons, in the prejudice of the common Stake, and to the Diſſervice of their Majeſties, who have call'd, or the People, who have ſent us hither.</p>
            <p>I hope again we ſhall not be like them as at other times murmuring at Gods providence, becauſe our Deliverance is wrought in meaſure, and keeps not up with the Vehemence of our deſires; or repining at ſuch Miſcarriages, as are ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably incident to all great Revolutions: Leſt our Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſhould become an occaſion of our Complaints, and ſlacken the full Accompliſhment of what we long for, with ſuch impatience. Let us not therefore look only on the Dark ſide of the Cloud, on our perſonal ſufferings, and <hi>fret our ſelves becauſe of the Evil doers,</hi> but behold the bright and amazing deliverance which God has wrought for us, and rather than ſtill be complaining, let us ſay with good old <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> when he loſt half his Eſtate, by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Accuſation of a falſe Informer, <hi>Yea, let them take all, ſince my Lord the King is Return'd in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, what ſhall we render unto the Lord, for all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits he has beſtow'd? Since the King is victorious over our Enemies, and we are thereby reſtor'd to all thoſe bleſſings, of which they had unjuſtly depriv'd us; ſurely the moſt juſt &amp; ſuitable Acknowledgment we can make, is to ſerve him, in every ſtation and Relation, wherein we have receiv'd advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; in our <hi>Religious,</hi> &amp; <hi>Private,</hi> and <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Capacities.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let it be right in our Eyes, to ſerve their Majeſties, in our Religious ſtations, by praying ſincerely and Earneſtly, for them, by whom the <hi>Houſe of Prayer</hi> is Reſtor'd to us, That the <hi>God of Iſrael</hi> would protect the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and eſtabliſh him, on the holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> where his Right Hand hath ſet him. Let us thus ſupport the hands of our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40137:10"/> 
               <hi>Deliverer,</hi> while his Armies are Fighting againſt <hi>Amalek;</hi> that being call'd out of the narrow Scene, where his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors Actions were confin'd for the Deliverance of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>Provinces,</hi> to aſſert the Liberties of <hi>Europe,</hi> againſt the Great Deſtroyer, he may ride Proſperouſly, becauſe of Truth, till he ſee the <hi>deſire of his Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it be right in our Eyes, to ſerve them with our <hi>Properties,</hi> and <hi>Private</hi> Intereſts, to enable them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat that Deliverance, for which his Majeſty ſo freely Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd his Life among us: At leaſt let it appear, that we are even in our low Eſtate, <hi>to our power, yea and beyond our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, willing of our ſelves,</hi> to ſupply the neceſſities, of which we have been a great occaſion, that our Loyalty and <hi>Zeal may provoke many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it be right in our Eyes, to ſerve them in our <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative</hi> capacities, by whom our old Laws are reſtor'd to us, and we to the Authority of making new ones, without any Challenge of ſuch a <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> as might ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both uſeleſs. Let us therefore give Conſent to, and offer matter for ſuch Laws, as will ſecure their Majeſties Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by promoting the Glory of God, and love and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will in the People, to their Majeſties, and to one another; by ſuppreſſing Idolatry and Vice; that by Righteous Laws, and ſevere Executions, and Good Examples, all Immorality and prophaneneſs may be puniſht, and if poſſible, put out of Countenance; that ſo, ſome ſtop may be given to that Flood of Impiety, That is roll'd in upon us, and is become too ſtrong for Pulpit Reproof, or ordinary Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>It is your Duty, (Moſt Noble Lords, Moſt Wiſe and Worthy Patriots) <hi>in this your day,</hi> to conſider things that make for peace, and to bear your Teſtimony againſt the crying Sins of this Generation, which call aloud for <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> or for <hi>Vengeance.</hi> By frequent Rapines, we have
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40137:10"/> almoſt loſt all Senſe of juſtice: By the commonneſs of ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and curſing, all Reverence for God, and holy things, Becauſe of theſe things, our Government is weakned, and Reproach'd, our Religion diſhonour'd, and the wrath of God cometh on the Children of diſobedience. You cannot ſerve their Majeſties more acceptably, who are great Examples of Vertue, and <hi>ſcatter iniquity with their eyes,</hi> nor ſettle their Thrones more ſecurely, which are beſt <hi>eſtabliſh't by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> nor your own peace more durably, than by retrieving the credit of our worſhip, and making it a ſupport of Vertue as well as of the Proteſtant Religion. Then <hi>Righteouſneſs and Peace will kiſs each other, Truth will look down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Glory ſhall dwell in our Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if after ſo great a deliverance, we ſhall again Return, or rather ſtill continue, in our follies and our Vanities, in our filthineſs and intemperance, in our Opreſſions and our plunders, eſteeming all right in our own eyes, whereby the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eye, or the pride of Life, is nouriſhed and pamper'd; we vainly truſt in Princes, or in Armies, tho never ſo brave and fortunate: Our boaſting of a true Religion is vain alſo, while we hold it in Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; nor will it ſtay long with us upon ſuch diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable terms. God knows how to puniſh, as well as to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: He can give us up to our own hearts luſts, to bite and devour, and conſume one another, by civil Wars; or he can hiſs for our Enemies from abroad, and bring upon us a <hi>Chuſhan,</hi> or an <hi>Eglon,</hi> or ſtir up the conquer'd <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> and arm the <hi>Canaanite</hi> yet in the Land againſt us; &amp; the Thorns in our Sides will prove Skiens and Daggers at our hearts, &amp; Fire come out of the Bramble, and deſtroy the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon.</hi> But I hope better things of you, while I thus ſpeak. Which God of his infinite Mercy grant for his ſake, who ſpeaks better things: <hi>To whom, with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:40137:11"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books lately Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>☞ THE State of the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>of</hi> Ireland, <hi>under the late King</hi> James<hi>'s Government; in which their Carriage towards him is juſtified, and the abſolute Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of their endeavouring to be freed from his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of ſubmitting to their preſent Majeſties, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated. The Fourth Edition, with Additions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bede Venerabili Opera quaedam Theologica nunc primum edita necnon Hiſtorica ante a ſemel edita acceſſerunt Egberti Archiepiſcopi Eborocenſis Dialogus de Eccleſiaſtica Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; Aldhelmi Epiſcopi Scireburnenſis Liber de Virginitate ex codicae antiquiſſimo emendatus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Defence of Pluralities, or holding Two Benefices with Cure of Souls, as now practiſed in the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>L. Annaei Flori Rerum Romanorum Epitome, interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, &amp; Notis illuſtravit Anna Tanaquilli Fabri Filia, Juſſu Chriſtianiſmi Regis, in uſum Sereniſſimi Delphini.</p>
            <p>De Presbyteratu Diſſertatio Quadripartita, Presbytera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Sacri Origines, Naturam Titulum, Officia &amp; Ordines, ab ipſis Mundi primordiis uſque ad Catholicae Eccleſiae conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matam Plantationem complectens. In qua Hierarchiae Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copalis Jus divinum &amp; Immutabile, ex Auctoritate Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum Canonice expoſitarum, &amp; Eccleſiaſticae traditionis Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragiis, breviter quidem, ſed luculenter aſſeritur.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40137:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
